John Kiriakou, welcome to the show.
Thanks, good to be with you. If you knew
that whistleblowing would have resulted
in 23 months in prison,
would have you done it?
I would have done it, but I would have
done it differently.
And this is something that I that I
advise would-be whistleblowers to do.
The The big big mistake I made was just
going out and speaking.
I tell people
don't say a word until you have an
attorney sitting in the chair next to
you to advise you. And not just an
attorney, but somebody skilled in
whistleblower defense. Somebody who can
really advise you on what to say, how to
say it, what words to leave out, what
words to couch.
And you know, you need that kind of
advice to protect yourself.
In what way? Like what parts of what you
did made you not protected? You know, at
the end of the day,
in my own case,
they wanted to get me and they were
going to get me. For me personally,
there was probably nothing that I could
have done to save myself, not really.
There's a
wonderful book, and forgive me for
digressing, there's a great book called
uh Three Felonies a Day by Dr. Harvey
Silverglate. He's a professor of law at
Harvard University. And he argues that
we are so overly criminalized in the
United States, so overly regulated, that
the average American on the average day,
going about his or her normal business,
commits three felonies every single day.
The point being, if they want to get
you, they're going to get you.
For me,
you know, at first they accused me of
espionage because they said that the
torture program was a top secret
program. In fact, it's illegal to
classify a crime for the purpose of
keeping it from the American people. So,
I don't think it would have held up in
court anyway, but they were determined
to get me. They got me on a minor
charge.
That's the price I had to pay.
When when that happened and you were
getting sentenced to prison,
what was going on in your mind back
then? Like what were you thinking?
>> You know, I kind of alternated between
periods of feeling sorry for myself
and periods of defiance.
Um
My ex-wife said something that turned
out to be really true and very helpful.
She said, "They have consistently
underestimated your resolve.
And if they thought this was going to
keep you silent, they didn't know you at
all."
And that really was the truth.
And so I thought, "Well,
they made me
kind of infamous
at least in transparency and and um
government circles. So, I'm going to I'm
going to use my access to the media
and just do the best that I can to
spread my message." My ex-wife told me
another thing that turned out to be very
important. She said,
"You have to keep talking about this
because eventually they're going to move
on to their next victim, which they did.
It was Ed Snowden.
And if you keep talking about it, your
side of the story will be the side of
record."
And so that's what I did, and she was
right.
>> Mhm. So, that was a big reason why you
doubled down?
>> Well, then there was a third reason
though, actually.
>> [laughter]
>> At at my sentencing in October of 2012,
my attorneys asked the judge to sentence
me to a minimum security work camp. No
bars on the windows,
no
locks on the doors. You're free to come
and go as you please. You're just on
your honor not to abscond.
And the plan was
I would probably do about 20 months.
Was going to keep my head down, keep my
mouth shut, do my 20 months, and go
home.
But the CIA was furious
that my sentence was so short.
And so they asked the uh Bureau of
Prisons to put me in an actual prison.
So, when I got there to turn myself in
at the camp, they said, "No, no, you're
across the street."
And I thought, "Okay, you're trained for
this. You can handle it.
And then I thought, you know what? If
they're going to try to screw me, I'm
going to screw them right back as best I
can using my constitutional rights to
freedom of speech and freedom of press.
And so that's what I did.
>> [laughter]
>> I mean, it's not like I had anything to
lose.
>> Yeah, I I guess that's the pace that I
was leaning into next is is like what's
the alternative? Like sitting there and
then like you've already come this far
and so I cuz when you're speaking there,
I'm putting myself in in your shoes and
going like, hey, like what would I do?
And I guess that there's something
there's something in that way like you
are going to get older and you're going
to think about all the things that you
didn't do and that would be one of the
one of them, especially after it being
exposed to what you were exposed to like
and being able to hide that. Do you
think that when you said earlier around
like
if they want to get you, they'll get you
because we're always we're committing
felonies all the time. If they want to
get you, they'll get you.
Why do you think that they want to get
you so bad? Oh, I aired the dirty
laundry in public. Yeah, that was an
easy [clears throat] one. They were
absolutely livid. It was one thing to
decline the torture training. It's an
entirely different thing to go public
about it.
They were furious.
>> So
did they ever come out and say what they
were doing was wrong?
>> Yeah, finally in 2018
when Gina Haspel was named CIA director
in her confirmation hearings before the
Senate Intelligence Committee she
apologized for the torture program.
Which is funny because she was the
godmother of the torture program.
But in response to
Senator Warner of Virginia,
his question on whether or not it was a
mistake, she said, yes, it was a mistake
and it shouldn't have been done.
>> And obviously you doubling down came
with a lot of really wild crazy stories
and we can definitely unpack some of
them today.
But
why do you think people don't believe in
your stories?
>> Oh, I think people believe in my
stories.
I do. I mean, you're going to get trolls
every once in a while. Um, and to tell
you the truth,
uh, there are a lot of stupid people out
there.
A lot.
Like I saw one I saw one comment the
other day,
the guy said,
"Oh, he took credit for everything the
CIA ever did." It's like,
[__]
I only talk about the period from, you
know, 1990 to 2004, and only the things
I was involved in, and only the Middle
East. So, you can't you can't please
everybody. And another thing, you know,
if you don't like the stories or the
shorts or the podcast, don't [__]
listen to them.
It's as simple as that.
>> [clears throat]
>> I'm fascinated to know this because
obviously, you said you're airing that
dirty laundry, which means they're doing
stuff that's dirty behind the scenes.
And my guess would be that they're not
stopping that. It's still continuing to
go on. When you
got sentenced and when you were in
prison, was there any other stuff that
you just kept being exposed to where
you're going like, "Whoa,
like this is so messed up."
>> On a on a daily basis.
>> On a daily basis.
>> in prison?
>> Yeah, in prison.
>> yeah. Yeah, on a daily basis.
>> In what way?
>> And that actually
got me into a a little bit more trouble
with the Bureau of Prisons.
And in which case I told them, "Bring
it. Bring it."
Um, the Bureau of Prisons is quite
literally the most corrupt,
most criminalized
entity I've ever encountered in
government. And I spent 20 years in
government, more than 20 years.
Um, listen, when you can
just pretend that the laws don't apply
to you,
because
who's the court going to believe? this
convict or the uniformed prison guard?
Well, I know what the truth is. I know
how how corrupt these prison guards are,
smuggling in drugs and phones and
tobacco and accepting bribes.
I mean, we see it every day. Listen,
when when
just as an example,
you get a shipment of let's say a pallet
of Pop-Tarts
to the to the commissary, okay?
The giant pallet of a thousand boxes of
Pop-Tarts shows up.
And then one of the prison guards backs
up his Ford F-150 pickup truck to the
loading dock and steals the entire
pallet of Pop-Tarts and then puts it all
on Facebook Marketplace or eBay to sell.
And the same with batteries and the same
with A&D ointment and the same with bags
of Starkist tuna.
That's crime. It's a felony.
When you've got two um
a special investigative service officers
who call me down to tell me that this
Kurdish prisoner called a number in
Pakistan and they told him to kill me,
right?
And then they tell him that I called a
number in Washington and they told me to
kill him,
hoping that we kill each other.
That's a felony.
But I'm the bad guy for reporting it to
the Huffington Post
and writing about it.
>> Do you feel like part of your mission
would then be to
be normalizing the discussion and not
making it as taboo? Like I feel
>> Oh, without a doubt. Yeah.
>> Because I feel I feel there's there's
there's this nature of
saying things about like
the deep state or saying saying saying
conspiracies and all this stuff and
people go like, "Oh, no, no, no, don't
talk about that. You're crazy." Do you
feel like a big part about about it is
like actually normalizing it so that
they cannot get away with as much?
>> You know, in a lot of ways that to me
that's an apples and oranges
situation.
Although, I will acknowledge that a lot
of things that people thought were crazy
conspiracies have turned out to be true.
We thought the COVID lab leak story was
a crazy conspiracy. It turned out to be
true. Nobody understood the depth of the
Jeffrey Epstein situation.
Much of that turned out to be true. Um
even things like Pizzagate, elements of
Pizzagate turned out to be true. So,
sure. There there are a lot of things
like that.
Uh the deep state's real.
I think uh
I think the only the only place you're
going to hear that it's not real is
MSNBC or MS Now or whatever they're
calling themselves this week. Uh
only because they've completely bought
into the deep state. I don't call it the
deep state. I call it the federal
bureaucracy.
The state. You can call it whatever you
want. It exists. You know, I say all the
time when when you've got CIA, NSA, DIA,
FBI,
NSC
officials
who serve for 25, 30, 35 years
knowing that presidents come and go
every four or eight years. And nobody
elects these bureaucrats.
That's the deep state.
It's a fact.
Whether we like to admit it or not.
>> And when we reference the deep state,
what specifically
are we referencing that they're doing?
>> Uh it depends kind of what you're
interested in.
In my case,
of course, it was all about torture.
They denied that there was any torture
program until I came out and called them
liars and then they admitted that there
was.
There was another whistleblower, we'll
never know who it was, who went public
with the information on the secret
prison system.
Uh we only learned from a whistleblower
that there was an international
rendition program. We only learned of uh
of the international assassination
program thanks to a leak to the Atlantic
Monthly.
So,
there's a lot out there that the deep
state is doing.
>> I discovered something really
interesting the other day and it was the
fact that most podcast listeners
eventually have this one thought, what
if I started my own show? In fact, there
was a study that shows that one in every
four podcast listeners want to start
their own podcast and that was me only a
short few years ago thinking about
starting my own show and fast forward to
now we went from zero to getting over 30
million views a month. My whole life has
changed. I get to be in rooms with
people I don't deserve to be in rooms
with and that's all thanks to
podcasting. Podcasting changed my life
so much and I know everyone that wants
to start a show if they start it, it can
change their life too, which is why I
created Pod Pro. Pod Pro is the greatest
podcast school in the world and the
reason I can say that with so much
confidence is it's because it's the only
school that has experts and podcasters
leading the way. People that are walking
the walk. If you are a podcaster or an
aspiring podcaster that is looking to
launch your show, then Pod Pro is for
you. You can go to the link in the
description or the show notes below or
go to thepodpro.com/apply and you can
put in your details and my team will
reach out to you directly. Once
again, go to the link in the description
or the show notes below or go to
thepodpro.com/apply.
Let's get right back to the show.
>> So, you you mentioned that there's
whistleblowers that we don't know of.
Why do we not know of them?
>> They've never gone public.
>> And the and the media have
have protected their identities.
>> Hm.
Which is again part of the
s-
part of the whole messaging and
everything just to protect the
identities.
>> You have to protect the identities.
You know, when you've got a
whistleblower protection law like we
have in this country, that does not
protect national security
whistleblowers,
there's a problem. If you're Listen, if
you're from the Department of
Agriculture and you want to say
something about waste, fraud, and abuse
in, you know, grain pricing, knock
yourself out. You're going to be a big
hero, you'll be on 60 Minutes.
If you're from CIA, FBI, NSA, DoD,
you're going to go to prison, probably
under the Espionage Act, and nobody's
going to be able to help you. How's that
fair?
>> It's so fascinating and I do want to
make this personal. I feel like we can
take this in a bit of a different angle
to a lot of the other shows you you go
on.
You've been through things that
most people could not even imagine, like
the CIA, federal prison,
losing everything
just for telling the truth,
but none of that gave you PTSD. From the
scans you did, the thing that you get
the most PTSD from is your divorce.
>> Right.
>> You've referenced your ex-wife before.
Why, out of everything, is the divorce
the most hard-hitting thing you've been
through?
>> I'm prohibited by court order from
talking about my ex-wife in any kind of
detail, but I think I can still answer
your question.
Um it's that
I was one of those people at This was
not unusual, but I was one of those
people who was able to compartmentalize.
The job was the job
and home life was home life.
And um
I knew that as hard as the job got, I
always had home I could go to.
And then I didn't have home.
And that's what kind of did me in.
That's what made it hard.
>> Right.
So, I guess you did a good job at being
able to not be defined by your job.
>> Oh, yeah. I worked hard at that.
Yeah.
>> W- When you say you worked hard at that,
what do you mean?
>> You have to have So many people make the
CIA their entire existence.
Everything in life is the CIA. They have
two, three, four, five, six even
marriages.
Just because family's never the focus,
it's always the job.
I worked for a guy who I really liked
and respected a lot.
And while we were overseas, his mother
died.
He was so upset. He said that
that he hadn't seen his mother five
years because he had been overseas. And
then when it was time for R&R, vacation,
rest and relaxation,
instead of going home to Ohio
to see his ever-aging mother,
he would go back to CIA headquarters and
just keep reading in on cases and see
what's going on and meeting and talking
and visiting and he's like, what the
heck was I thinking?
And he said, now my mother's dead. I
have I have nobody. Everybody's gone.
And I remember thinking, boy,
I don't want to end up like that.
So many people do.
Uh another thing, too, at the CIA,
they like that the culture is closed.
So they have affinity groups for every
interest under the sun
so that you never have to leave the CIA.
We had a softball league. I played
softball every year. We had a flag
football league. We had an LGBTQ
uh group. There was a choir. There was a
quilting club. There was a cooking club.
There was this one and that one and
you know, you could buy baseball
tickets, football tickets at the
employee activity center.
Anything you wanted to do in life, you
could do it right there
at the CIA. And I remember thinking,
that's just not right. Yeah, I would
play softball, but anything else, come
on. What are you doing?
But the idea behind it is that
everybody's cleared
and so you can talk about work while
you're quilting or playing baseball or
whatever.
It's easier for everybody. And then you
don't have to worry about security.
>> Do you think there's anything behind
that? Why do they make it so Why do they
want you so stuck in the CIA? Like
what's
Because like if you mentioned before
like
there's so much power in having a home
to go back to.
Do you think there's something they're
trying to do to not make you have a
home?
>> No, on the contrary. They want you to
marry another CIA person.
That way everybody's bought in.
That way nobody questions why you're out
all night long twice a week.
You know?
Um they encourage the culture encourages
agency romances.
I've said many times on podcast that I
worked for a deputy director
who was married five times
and all five of his wives
began as his secretary.
And that's not unusual.
That's just the culture.
>> But surely as you mentioned you saw
great power in being able to separate
them.
>> Oh, yeah.
>> Right. And so but what I'm fascinated to
know is like why are they encouraging
that? Is it because
the people are going to do the job
better? They're going to actually make
sure that they
>> Not even necessarily. I think it's that
everybody's going to stay in line.
It's much easier to control everybody
when they're fully bought in.
>> Right. So when you're in the CIA is
there a series of things you like
have to hide from people? Like you have
to be very secretive about your life in
a sense. And so if they can keep
everyone in your family under the roof
then there's less chance of it being
leaked.
>> Yeah.
And there are CIA families. I worked
with people where you know mother,
father, two, three kids were all CIA.
That's not unusual at all. I worked with
three different guys whose dads had been
either deputy director for operations or
deputy director for intelligence. They
love you know legacies. They love
families because everybody's bought in.
Um and you know you you you do have to
lie to everybody at least to some
extent, even when you're not formally
undercover.
When I was an analyst, I was not
undercover. I was an overt employee.
But, I just made it a practice of saying
State Department when people asked me
where I worked.
I was living in
Excuse [clears throat] me.
I was living in Maryland at the time and
became friendly with my next-door
neighbor. And, uh
he was a carpenter.
And, he asked me where I worked. I said,
"I'm at the State Department." And, "Oh,
what do you do at the State Department?"
Well, the training was you tell them
something that sounds so boring that
they won't ask any follow-up questions.
So, I said that I was involved in
training people in conducting trade
negotiations.
And, he's like, "Oh."
And, then that was it, which was great.
And, then one day
I left for work. He left a couple of
minutes after I did.
And, I didn't notice, but he
was following me all the way to work.
Not on purpose, just because he was
going in the same direction that I was
going. And, he saw me pull off on the
CIA exit. There's an exit that
specifically goes directly into the CIA
compound.
And, then later that day he came over
and he said, "Hey, I just wanted to
ask you about something that I saw today
that kind of struck me as funny." And,
he said, "I I saw you pull into the CIA
today." And, I said, "Buddy," I said,
"just keep it between us, huh?"
And, he was like, "I knew it. I knew
nobody would have a job that was so
boring that they loved so much." And, I
said, "Well, you can see why I I don't
want to talk about it."
And, he respected it.
>> Mhm.
>> [gasps]
>> I I just wanted to like I I think about
connections in in life, right? Like
the deepest connections that I have are
the ones that
kind of I feel like I can be an open
book with.
But, if you're constantly trying to hide
the
the things that you're doing and
actually spending most of your time
doing,
do you find that it's harder to connect
with people?
>> I I never had trouble connecting with
people, but sure. I I worked with others
who had trouble connecting with people
outside that community.
I always had outside interests.
Things that weren't CIA specific.
Um in fact, one of my bosses
complimented me one time
after an operational meeting where he
said that he'd never seen anybody able
to speak on so many varied issues as I
was. It was like baseball and opera and
politics and I forget what the other one
was.
Um but just it was because I had these
outside interests. There was more to
life than just the CIA for me. And for
for most case officers,
there isn't. It's just the job.
>> Yeah, I've seen you
debate other former CIA officers. Um I
interviewed one of them, Andrew
Bustamante.
What about
their world view and your world view, do
you feel differs?
>> A lot.
A lot. People ask me regularly if Andrew
Bustamante is still on the CIA payroll.
And I say, I have no idea. He sure
sounds like he is,
but I have no idea. I mean, if he loved
the CIA so much
and he was so important
to the success of the CIA,
why did he and his wife both resign? And
why is he talking about fleeing the
United States for another country?
You'd have to ask him.
>> Well, when I asked him
on the show, I was
I was explaining how like why he's mov-
he he he wants to move and he and his
whole reasoning was just about
wanting his kids to experience a third
world country so that they can
appreciate America the most.
>> Sure. I mean, who wouldn't want to get
malaria when you're 6 years old?
>> Makes you a stronger person, right?
>> Jeez.
>> What else do you do you feel like makes
him defend his stance and defend the CIA
so much?
>> I think he's a true believer.
I don't think he's a dissident in any
way. I think he's just a he's a yes man
for the CIA.
May I add something?
>> Yeah.
>> Andrew also um
I think he's trying to prove a lot to
himself.
He was never an operations officer.
Never. I cringe every time I hear people
say, "Andrew Bustamante walked the
walk." Actually, no, no, he didn't. He
was a special operations officer or
staff operations officer. That's an
assistant to the operations officers.
So, this notion that he was running out
there running around the world grabbing
bad guys, kicking asses, and taking
names is just simply not true.
But listen, that's his that's his thing
and he's going with it and it makes a
handsome living for him, so God bless. I
I'm that's none of my business.
But I'm just saying that I don't think
he's entirely honest.
>> Mhm.
How much is
all of the decisions that get made
involved around money and power?
>> Inside the CIA?
>> Yeah.
>> At the higher levels, it's almost
entirely about power.
Not money. Money is ever flowing, never
ending, bottomless pit of money. You
never have to worry about money. There's
going to be money for whatever you want
to do.
Um but once you get into the senior
service, it's it's all about power and
empire building, right? You you get to
the senior service and you're going to
constantly try to expand your empire so
that it makes you
prepared for the next higher level and
the next one after that and after that.
I I worked with a guy
I worked with a guy when we were junior
analysts together.
He might have been one grade senior to
me. I think he was actually cuz he came
in with a PhD.
And um
10 years later he's the associate deputy
director.
So for a lot of people it's just about
the power.
Another thing too, one of the one of the
senior operations officers told me, a
guy that I really really liked and
respected and trusted, he said, you
know, one of the things that he always
hated
was the people who rose through their
career most quickly were the were the
ones who spent the least amount of time
overseas.
So he said,
you know, we say that the job of the CIA
is to recruit spies to steal secrets.
And that's true.
But if you just want to get promoted
over and over and over and over again,
you stroke the important people back at
headquarters. And you don't go overseas
to recruit spies to steal secrets.
>> Mhm.
So I get what Okay, so the less travel
you do, the more you can climb up the
ranks. And so for people trying to climb
up the ranks, it's not advantageous for
them to leave.
>> Uh there was a guy
who was passed over for deputy director
when I was there. He had been
chief of like four four different giant
stations.
And I remember hearing his
qualifications and saying to my boss,
"Wow, he's done everything.
Why didn't he get this job?"
And the the insider that you see in the
hall for the last 8 years, he's the one
who got the job.
And he said, "Because this guy's been
overseas doing actual spy work,
and at headquarters nobody's heard of
him."
Cuz he's overseas.
But then the guy that's at home shaking
hands and running to the White House two
or three days a week, everybody's heard
of him.
So they're going to give him the job.
It's not fair. It's antithetical to the
way it should be.
>> It's fascinating because isn't the
primary goal
of the CIA, I mean,
I'm not fully educated it it, but like
it's it's to protect the United States
from everywhere else in the world?
>> Yeah, it's to recruit spies to steal
secrets
and to analyze those secrets so that the
policy maker can make the best informed
policy.
>> Yeah.
See, one of the pieces that I didn't
resonate with with Andrew Bustamante's
worldview
and we went back and forth on it a fair
bit,
um
was
was he he was saying that money's the
only thing that matters, basically. And
he was trying and he was explaining that
money's the only objective measure of
success.
>> That's not true.
>> And and
>> See, but this is coming from a guy who
never recruited a source in his entire
career.
>> Yeah, and and he's like, if your net
worth is not over a million dollars, no
one cares about you. And he went all
along this whole thing and and we had a
bit of back course and the way it ended
was he was he was just calling me young
and what do I know about the world? And
but but the thing one of the things that
I I just struggled with and and even
from the very start of this
conversation, you were explaining how
that the reason the divorce hurt the
most is because
it was the thing that gave you a home to
come back to
which then shows that yeah, there's all
the progressions and there's everything
else in your career and all of that, but
the real power for you, which is why it
hurt the most, is the fact that you were
able to separate yourself from that and
actually build a a home and something
that feels like the volume can turn down
in your life, which has nothing to do
with with with the money. And so, I
guess do you think that that's an area
where you guys would definitely disagree
with your views?
>> Yeah.
Listen, Andrew simply doesn't know what
he's talking about.
It's not It's not the money at all.
Not from any angle.
Um
yes, a majority of sources who agree to
be recruited are doing it for the money.
But there are many many many other
reasons why people agree to be
recruited. Many other reasons.
>> Yeah. Yeah.
>> With all due respect, he doesn't what
he's talking about.
>> Yeah.
When you were
like
when you were in
in service and you were um you're
working with the CIA
>> [sighs and gasps]
>> was there any main things that caught
you by surprise? Like before going into
it and then you dive into the line of
work that you were doing, like did Is
there anything that like really shocked
you?
That like comes to your mind straight
away?
>> Really shocked me?
Well, there were a couple of things,
yeah, that really shocked me that I I
can't talk about. There When I first
joined as a junior junior analyst um
yeah, there were there were some things.
I remember the first four or five six
weeks, I would just sit at my desk and
say, "Wow."
Like I had no idea.
And then I I say something in my first
book
when I switched to operations
um I'm sitting on one side of a
partition and I'm going through
thousands of pages of operational files
on Greek terrorism.
And
I'm going through this file and I said,
"Oh my god." And this voice from the
other side of the partition, somebody I
didn't know, says "You going through the
Greek files?"
And I said, "Yeah." And he says, "That's
what everybody says when they go through
the Greek files."
And I was like, "Wow,
>> [sighs and gasps]
>> man."
Like that was some bad [__] in the '60s
and '70s and the '80s.
>> So why are you not able to share what
you read in the files?
>> Oh, it's still it's still They call it
currently improperly classified.
>> Damn.
>> Mhm.
>> Okay.
And so what's the main reason that a lot
of the information is hidden?
Like what is the main reason?
>> Mostly to protect sources and methods.
If there's a CIA source, especially if
that source is still alive, you have to
protect the identity at all costs.
>> Right, right. So So when the go and try
and find the the
the secrets and everything, they're
finding the sources certain people, and
to and to get the secrets out, they need
to
>> if if you're a CIA case officer, let's
say, and you need to penetrate, you
know, ISIS.
You don't look like you could fit into
ISIS.
So, what you do is you recruit somebody
who does fit into ISIS, or maybe is
already in ISIS.
And that's how you get your information.
That's how you disrupt the next attack.
You have that guy working for you,
coming out and reporting back to you.
It's the same everywhere.
[clears throat]
>> You mentioned on the Jack New podcast
that
like some of the different things that
you used you saw like like drones that
were in tiny little
tiny little
>> little dragonflies.
>> little dragonflies and stuff.
Was there any
any times where you were on missions
where you felt
unsafe with what some of the other
countries were doing?
>> That's a good question.
Um
Not really.
In In almost all the operations that I
ever worked on,
they were they were joint with liaison.
So, we were working together. I mean,
some some services, rather, are better
than others.
The Pakistanis weren't as
technologically sophisticated as we
were, for example.
There are other countries I was working
with where, you know, I just didn't
trust them very much.
And then there were some, especially in
Middle East, where, you know, we trusted
each other with our lives.
But no, I never felt like I was in
danger because of the service.
There were a couple of odd
events, I guess.
I was working
jointly with one service.
And it's supposed to be joined. And I
left my hotel, realized I'd forgotten my
wallet. So,
when I got to the exit of hotel, I
turned around and went back to up to the
room. There's a guy in my room. He's got
my phone unscrewed.
I said, "What are you doing?" He says,
"Fixing the phone." I said, "There's
nothing wrong with the phone." He says,
"Now it works even better."
I said, "Come on, you guys. We're
supposed to be working together here.
You're bugging my room? Why don't you
bug the bad guys' room?"
And I was just Well, I finally got to
the meeting. I was like, "You have to
stop. Either we're going to do this
together or we're not."
"What were they doing to your phone?"
"Bugging it."
"What does that mean?" "Putting a
microphone in it."
"The guy on your team?" "Yeah."
Damn.
Talk to me about trust then. Do you find
and build great trust with the people
you're working with or is there a lot of
skepticism? Well, when
with other CIA people, you mean? Or
foreign liaison? Other CIA people? Oh,
yeah, yeah. You have to trust each other
with your lives. You have to. Right. But
then the foreign people you obviously
not trust. Yeah, you know, Ronald Reagan
used to say trust but verify.
So, you're going to trust the Brits, the
Canadians, the Australians, the New
Zealanders.
They're the only ones that you trust
for.
The only ones. Everybody else you have
to keep one eye open. Yeah. Yeah.
So, just before we recorded,
you mentioned that
you know,
you had a hard time with one of your
sons thinking that you put him in a
sticky situation and it it
it kind of like
made the relationship struggle a little
bit from from that. Was that one of
those things that like was that one of
those negative things that happened from
from you being the whistleblower? Like
was that one of the things making it
harder for your family? Yeah, that was
that was one of the things. There there
was a I put a great deal of pressure on
my family by doing this.
I didn't realize it was going to be the
major international story that it was. I
don't think any of us did.
Um on either side, but it did. It took
on a life of its own. And so it it
caused a lot of pressure and a lot of
friction.
>> Was it a very thought out decision
speaking up on it or was it
>> Well, I mean I I considered it for a
week. We talked about it for a week in
advance. Should I do it? Should I not do
it? And um
>> Who's we?
>> My my wife and I.
And uh and I decided to do it.
You know, in part I did it for selfish
reasons, for self-preservation
because a a reporter for ABC News had
called me and said that he had heard
from a source that I had tortured Abu
Zubaydah, this Al-Qaeda prisoner. I
said, "Absolutely untrue. I never laid a
hand on him or on any other prisoner
ever." But then it became apparent to me
that the source was at the White House,
that the story was leaking from
somewhere, that there was this torture
program, and that they were going to
blame me.
And I said, "Oh, no, you don't."
And so I called them back and I said,
"I'll give you your interview." And I
decided just to tell the truth.
Hm. Yeah. Yeah, I've said before, I wish
I could say
that, you know, I stood up for a moral
purpose and I told them that and that
wasn't it at all.
They were just going to try to pin it on
me and I was like,
"Oh, no, you don't.
I'm going to I'm going to come out first
with the truth and let the American
people make their decision who they
believe."
>> And
is there anything you can share that
the CIA doing that might be affecting
just everyday people?
>> Oh, I think that there are a million
questions out there about tech.
You know, post-9/11, the CIA got a
congressional waiver to begin investing
in tech companies beginning with
Palantir. CIA was the very first
investor in Palantir. CIA has a venture
capital fund called In-Q-Tel, in which
they invest billions of dollars, or have
invested billions of dollars over the
years in tech startups, so that they can
use that tech in espionage.
Well,
is the tech being used against
Americans?
Ed Snowden says it is.
Tom Drake says it is. Julian Assange
says it is.
You know, whistleblowers from
the big tech companies, you know, Google
and Yahoo and Twitter and Facebook and
all these other ones, they say it is.
I think it is.
>> How do you think that plays out? The
controlling what we see online?
>> Probably in part.
But what is more frightening to me
is that
the CIA and NSA are not allowed to spy
on Americans, right? It's even a part of
NSA's charter that it cannot spy on
Americans.
And they do spy on Americans.
>> Yeah, do do you think they they cannot
spy on Americans, but they can make you
tick something that allows them to
like like like
you know how there's like pop-ups on
Instagram or whatever, or just a new
terms and conditions or whatever, and
then all of a sudden they're listening
to every word you say. Do you think
there's something involved with the CIA
and
the higher-ups that like
is manipulating the way that they can
like listen to everything? Like they're
like like listening to the phones and
>> Well, we know from the Vault 7
revelations from 2017, uh Joshua Schulte
uh is alleged to have uh sent
the crown jewels of the CIA to
WikiLeaks, and he says exactly that.
That they are listening to us
constantly.
You know, just recently, I was on the
phone with a friend of mine and I was
saying that uh uh I've gotten some death
threats lately from some truly unhinged
lunatics.
And he said
"Oh, you should take a concealed carry
course." I said, "No, I've I've taken a
concealed carry course and I had a
concealed carry permit." Uh but because
I have a felony conviction, I had to
give up my gun and I can only get it
back if I receive a presidential pardon.
Literally as soon as we hung up the
phone
every single ad on my Facebook feed was
for a kill a concealed carry class.
Every single ad.
So, you know they're listening.
They tell you in the terms of uh use
that they're that they're listening.
But, it's for a it's for a better
advertising experience, right? At least
that's what they want us to believe.
Well, Joshua Schulte told us that the
CIA is able to, you know, remotely take
over control of your car by hacking into
into its computer or it's able to turn
your smart TV speaker into a microphone
so that it broadcasts back to them
everything that's being said in the room
even when the TV's off.
And those are just two out of dozens and
dozens of technical operations that he
revealed to us.
So, no, I don't trust the CIA or NSA or
the FBI or any of these other
national security agencies to protect my
civil rights and and civil liberties.
No.
>> It's crazy. It It does make me think
around how you like
you really can't trust anything that you
see.
And it's concerning the amount people
take things as gospel and run with it.
Well, like I think those it wasn't that
I don't know the exact numbers of like
50% of the accounts online are bots.
>> Right. 50%?
>> Something crazy like this.
>> Yeah.
>> And and and so then you just go, "Okay,
like
if I see something online, I've got to
like look at it twice and maybe not take
it as gospel and maybe do my own
research and figure out why that's being
presented to me in the first place
because
if they can
if they can listen to a conversation
that you're having in real life and then
moments later pop up a a perfect ad and
everyone listening to this has
experienced this, pop up a perfect ad of
that thing,
whether it's swimming trunks or a towel
or hand soap, whatever it is. Watch me
get all these right now.
>> Yeah.
>> Right. If they can do that, it makes me
question
what else they can do.
>> Mhm.
>> How can they do that so quickly? Surely
if they planned something or they
planned a agenda that they're trying to
push or whatever it is, they could
probably get it on your phone relatively
easy.
>> Sure.
>> And so, then it does make me make me
wonder.
>> And you've seen You've seen
investigative journalists um
uh experiment with phone tracking
systems, too. Where
I when you could take the phone the
battery out of the phone and they take
the battery out of the phone, but the
backup battery continues to send a ping
showing your location.
What's the point of taking the battery
out of the phone if it's still tracking
you?
>> Wait, what's this? Can you explain this?
>> Yeah, the not the current phones that we
have, but 10 years ago you used to be
able to take the battery out of the
phone, right? If you wanted privacy.
Um but there were backup batteries in
phones. And so, even if you take the
battery out, the backup battery
continued to send a ping showing your
location.
Who's it reporting to? If I take the
battery out of the phone, that means I
don't want the phone tracking me.
But it continued to track.
And now you can't take the battery out
of the phone. Even when you shut the
phone off, it continues to track your
location.
>> Do you think anything's changed
dramatically since the CIA has started
investing in big tech companies?
>> I do.
I do. When I was in the CIA,
most of the spy gadgets that we used, we
just
we just bought, you know, on the open
market. There used to be these shops in
London, New York, and Washington called
the spies the spy store the spy shop,
one of the other. It was over on Hem
Street, 18th.
Um
but it was it was cheaper, faster,
easier to just buy something that had
already been invented than it was to
just reinvent the wheel from scratch and
spend a million dollars in development.
Now you just buy it off of I mean for a
while we would just buy it off of
Amazon. Well, now with these
partnerships with big tech, the CIA's
got its own, you know, satellites and
all kinds of crazy advanced things. A
guy that I sat next to for years who I
really I liked and respected deeply is
now the director of technology for the
for the whole CIA managing these
relationships that we have we that the
that the CIA has with big tech.
Mhm, scary.
It It does What does it end?
>> Yeah. And then with AI and all the rest
of it coming in you just go
I wonder the amount of control. Maybe
Bustamante's leaving cuz he needs to
escape.
>> [laughter]
>> Well, you know, maybe the third world
country is so that we can maybe be
hidden a bit more.
>> The first thing he had to do is is heed
the CIA training do not attract
attention to yourself by getting rid of
the Sideshow Bob hair do. And then maybe
he can move overseas and not be so
easily noticed.
>> Do you think that's the thing why he got
rid of the hair?
>> Yeah, I do.
>> What do you mean?
>> Yeah, you can't have hair like that in
the CIA. He did not have hair like that
in the CIA.
Don't attract attention to yourself. If
you're going undercover
and you look like Sideshow Bob from The
Simpsons,
you're not
doing cover very well.
>> [laughter]
>> Sorry.
>> Sacha Baron Cohen is crazy, man.
>> [laughter]
>> But he looks like Sacha Baron Cohen,
right?
>> Yeah.
>> I mean
>> I'm waiting for him to break out into,
you know, HMS Pinafore.
>> [laughter]
[gasps]
>> Is Is there Is there an actual between
you two?
>> No.
>> I met the guy one time. We had a good
debate. It was all in good fun.
>> Yeah.
>> We We take a little poke at each other
every once in a while, but he's he's a
good guy.
>> Yeah. No, he's cool. He was lovely.
Invited me to his home, and I I
appreciated it. It was It was great. Can
I want to talk about some of the the
the massive world events that have
happened, and
you've been experienced You've
experienced some of them. You've got
inside on some of them. Um some of them
being during your time working with the
CIA.
If we go back to the 9/11,
where were you at that time?
>> Well, yeah, I was in I was in CIA
headquarters at the at the
Counterterrorism Center.
Um that morning
the director of counterterrorism, Cofer
Black, and I had a meeting at the White
House with Condoleezza Rice scheduled
for 9:00.
And so at 8:10
the driver called me to say that the car
was ready.
They were waiting for us at the South
at the South door. I walked over to
Cofer's office to tell him that the car
was ready to take us to the White House.
And um
these are the days before you could
watch TV on your computer. So, Cofer's
secretary had a little
um a little TV, like a 5-in TV, on her
desk, and one of the towers of the World
Trade Center was burning.
So, I went up there, and I looked at it.
I said, "What happened to the World
Trade Center?"
And she said, "A plane hit it."
And I said
and I've said this before, because I'm
so smart, I said, "You know, that
happened once before in 1930. A plane
hit the the Empire State Building, but
it was pouring rain. It was really foggy
that day. It's so crystal clear today.
How can you not see that you're flying
into the World Trade Center?"
And just as I said the words, the second
plane hit.
And then she turned to me and she said,
"Did you see that or did I imagine it?"
Then I ran back to my office. I said,
"Guys, two planes just hit both towers
of the World Trade Center. I think we're
under attack." Everybody ran up to
Cofer's office. There were these TVs
that were hanging from the the ceiling.
It was like CNN, MSNBC. I don't think
there was a Fox News yet. Um there may
have been. I don't recall, but BBC and
Canal Plus and the Russians and the
Chinese.
And it was all the same scene.
And then, you know, a plane hits the
Pentagon.
And it's like, "Oh, now this is this is
what they've been talking about for
months." We knew something was going to
happen for months. And we just didn't
know where where it was going to be. The
conventional wisdom was
that Al-Qaeda was going to hit another
American Embassy overseas, take down a
big embassy.
We just didn't think it was going to be
here in the United States.
>> So
So you knew something was happening.
>> On on July 6th of that year, I've told
this story many times, but on July 6th
that year, totally, completely normal
day for me. I was hosting a group of
Middle Eastern intelligence officers at
headquarters. We did this every day. You
do it a day full of briefings. You take
them upstairs to shake the director's
hand, get a photo op. You exchange
gifts. You take them out to a fancy
dinner that night. And the next day you
do it with a group from a different
country.
Every day.
So that day, and these are all like
mid-level guys at the major, lieutenant
colonel level.
So that day I was hosting them and I
scheduled a briefing, a 1-hour briefing
with a very junior analyst on Al-Qaeda.
So,
when it came time for the briefing,
instead of this junior analyst coming,
Cofer Black comes with the director of
operations for the Osama bin Laden
group. And I was so surprised, I jumped
up. I said, "Oh, gentlemen,
this is Cofer Black. He's the director
of the CIA's Counterterrorism Center,
and this is the
head of operations."
And Cofer sat down
with his grave tone,
and he said, "Something terrible is
going to happen.
We don't know exactly when or where,
but we know it's going to be an attack
on an unprecedented scale.
We're hearing chatter coming from the
Al-Qaeda training camps, where camp
uh commanders are talking to their
students, and they're crying on the
phone, and saying, "I'll see you in
paradise."
We're hearing
code words for a massive attack. The
honey salesman's coming with vast
quantities of honey.
There's going to be a giant wedding, an
enormous football match. All code words
for an attack."
He said, "I'm begging you.
If you have any sources inside Al-Qaeda,
please help us." And they just kind of
sat there and looked at him.
Nobody said anything.
At the end of the day,
I sent them back to the hotel,
told them I'd pick them up in 2 hours
for dinner, and then I went over to
Cofer's office to thank him for taking
the time. The guy's important. He's
meeting with the president every day.
And he's going to take an hour and come
and talk to these guys?
So, I said, "Cofer, I have to ask you,
I don't work on Al-Qaeda.
Were you saying that just for their
benefit, or were you serious?"
And he said, "No, I was deadly serious.
Something terrible is going to happen."
And then 2 months later, it happened.
I knew immediately it was what he was
talking about.
>> Mhm.
So,
there's so many different different
stories around 9/11 and so many
different things of conspiracies and
different things of what people
think it happened.
For you, like
how how
how much clarity do you have and how
much confidence do you have in what
actually happened?
>> I'm confident.
I don't believe it was the Jews,
the Saudi royal family, the lizard
people,
um
Dick Cheney, the Bushes,
thermite paint that was
put on the wall in the 1970s,
all the bolts were removed by Larry
what's-his-name. No.
Al-Qaeda did it.
>> Damn.
>> Mhm.
>> [gasps]
>> Yeah. I I
I think it's just a fascinating one
because
if we tie back into how you see
people being out of control of the
media, especially if they can listen to
us and they can push whatever they want,
it makes me wonder with how
uh
with the power of social media now, like
how much can they hide everything that
they do because I guess if they can just
flood your feed with whatever they want,
how much can they hide all of their
laundry and how much can they just
dissolve things? And you see this happen
all the time, right? You see you see
all of a sudden COVID's the biggest
problem and then next minute Black Lives
Matter happens and then all of a sudden
COVID's irrelevant and then that this
happens and then Epstein
>> wag the dog situation. It certainly can
be.
And then when you've got
when you've got the law that banned
propagandization of the American people
effectively overturned in 2015-2016,
you're right. Of course, people are
going to think there's a conspiracy.
There could be.
I think on 9/11 there wasn't.
I think the only conspiracy was a
conspiracy of silence. I think the
Israelis probably had advanced warning
that
there was going to be an attack in the
United States. That's why there were so
many Israeli intelligence officers in
New York that day.
Um but they they knew that if we were
going to be attacked, we were going to
go hog wild and just kill as many
Muslims as we could, which is exactly
what happened.
You know, thus helping the Israelis.
So, I think that
was a conspiracy.
But um
Yeah, I can see why people believe what
they believe. I I also continue to
believe that they're wrong in their
conclusions, but I understand why they
believe so.
>> Mhm.
>> What about Epstein? Did How long did you
know Did you know well before it all
came out what was going on?
>> No. No idea.
No. Never encountered the man, never
heard his name.
No.
But
I for one believed the conspiracies
surrounding Epstein. I did not believe
Pizzagate. I'll say that. And much of
Pizzagate turned out to be true. At
least with the release of this most
recent tranche, it appears that much of
Pizzagate turned out to be true.
Um
Planet Pizza, whatever it was called,
Comet Pizza, whatever. There's no
basement. There's no holding pen for
children to be trafficked from Hillary
Clinton. That was all silliness.
But
I don't think we'll ever get to the
bottom of what was meant by beef jerky
and grape soda.
You know, the beef jerky man's coming to
teach us how to make the beef jerky.
He's bringing really high-quality beef
jerky.
He's going to show us how to prepare the
beef jerky. He's going to dry the beef
jerky.
We're going to have the beef jerky set
aside from everything else. Nobody ever
talks about eating the beef jerky.
And if you like beef jerky so much, why
don't you just go to Walmart and buy it?
Right? So, what is it? What are we
talking about here? Are we talking about
children?
And the reason why nobody's talking is
because the statute of limitations has
expired and it doesn't do them any good
to talk.
Why would they?
But then there are other things in the
Epstein files.
Kathryn Ruemmler,
who was the White House counsel.
The White House counsel.
And
a woman whom Barack Obama described as
his most trusted aide.
First of all,
she was in constant touch with Epstein,
calling her calling him um
um Uncle Jeff,
you know, my best friend.
How? Why?
And then repeatedly trying to introduce
him
to John Brennan, the director of the
CIA. To do what?
Why would she need to broker a meeting
between Jeffrey Epstein, a convicted
pedophile,
and the director of the CIA?
Yeah, we're never going to get answers.
And then when the president says
that
he doesn't care what the law says, he's
not releasing the rest of the documents.
Remind you, the vote was 419
to 1 in the House and 99 to nothing in
the Senate. He signed it and then said,
"Eh, I'm not going to release this. What
are you going to do about it? You going
to sue me?"
Go ahead and sue me.
Why?
To protect whom?
So, I don't know.
I believe that conspiracy.
Yeah, I I saw somebody just recently in
the media uh criticizing Dan Bongino.
Um
I don't know Dan Bongino well. I've met
him a couple of times.
Uh we probably disagree on most issues,
but I've always found him to be uh um an
honest and direct person.
And that's why even though I disagree
with him on these major issues, I was
actually very pleased when he was named
the deputy director of the FBI because I
believed that he wanted the truth to
come out.
And you remember in that last part let
uh sorry. You remember in the last um
uh press conference that he did with Pam
Bondi and Kash Patel,
the look on his face showed him to be
furious.
Furious. They're talking about the
Epstein files.
And he resigned soon after that.
And now
he says, "Well, his job at the FBI was
make sure
that that the rules were followed and
you know,
this, that." And no, that's not at all
what you said. You said you were going
to release the Epstein files.
That's what you said.
And now you're like, "Well, no, I never
said I wanted to release the Epstein
files. What I said is I wanted, you
know, the truth to No, no, no, no, no.
No.
So, you know, so many of us believed
that the swamp was actually going to get
drained.
Every Everybody just became a swamp
monster.
>> Nothing was drained.
>> Why do you think they amplified it to
any degree in the first place then if
they had never no intentions of
releasing?
>> that they did have intentions of
releasing.
And I think that what Marjorie Taylor
Greene has told us is true, that so many
important, powerful, famous people were
involved. People who give millions upon
millions of dollars to the two political
parties
that everybody was just like, "Oh,
better not to rock the boat."
>> Damn.
>> Mhm.
It's crazy the pull that one person had
though on all of the people. It does
make me wonder
how that even played out and how that
even
>> I I really don't wonder about [laughter]
it.
You don't? I'm 100% confident he was an
Israeli access agent.
But with the release of this last
tranche of 3 million pages,
he appears to have also been working for
the CIA, for the FBI, for the British
MI5 and MI6, for the Germans,
and he sought contact with the Russians
repeatedly,
but they couldn't come to an agreement.
>> What do you think is the biggest concern
for
corruption in the future?
>> You know, I
I think that the biggest concern is that
the law is um
is unevenly administered.
So, if you're one of the insiders, one
of the swells,
you can do anything you want.
And the the Supreme Court has
essentially said, you know, corruption's
fine.
Go ahead and be corrupt.
Any president can be corrupt.
You can't prosecute a president for
anything that he does while he's
president.
We've never had the Supreme Court ever
say something like that before.
And so now, you know, corruption is
okay, grifting is okay, enriching
oneself is okay.
How do we How do we make it back from
here?
Nobody in Congress has the guts to
to sponsor legislation or to pass
legislation, and certainly no president
would would undercut his own
position and his own authority
not at this point.
So, I'm not sure how we recover from
this.
>> Yeah. What about like
agendas and propaganda online?
And and I know that propaganda is a bit
of a weird word in itself, but like
it's clear that we see a lot of agendas
online that are being pushed massively.
Like for example, like a
a
manosphere documentary will come out,
but they'll never release a
feminism documentary as an example,
right? That's just one thing. Like the
the the stuff that's being amplified
is
it's clearly agenda. Um you know, even
I've had like someone that I was
connected with who
was more of like a he was he was more of
like a news reporter, but independent
and he was blowing up in Australia and
he and he was making all this great
content that was clear that he was
writing and then boom, a collaborative
post with news.com.au
and it's a completely different
script that's clearly agenda and I
message him and I say, "Hey, like I know
you didn't write this." And he's like,
"No, I'll be honest, I didn't."
Like it's clear that there's an agenda
going on.
What are your thoughts on on that and
how they're controlling a narrative with
a lot of things that we're seeing
online?
>> Yeah, I think we're so far down that
road that uh
it's virtually impossible to get back.
When I was a little kid
um Walter Cronkite was
the guy that most everybody watched for
news, CBS News. There was talk of Walter
Cronkite running for president or chosen
for vice president on an independent
ticket because everybody in America
trusted Walter Cronkite. And it wasn't
just Walter Cronkite, it was I mean
every network had these had these old
men who had been working in journalism
for decades and everybody just trusted
them. You trusted them that when you
tuned in for the evening news at 6:30 or
7:00
you're going to get it straight without
any editorialization.
And that's like
laughable now, quaint.
Um
on both the left and the right.
I I'll give you two examples.
Um
I And I've said this many times. I was a
third-generation Democrat. And I left
the Democratic Party years ago because
to me it moved too far to the right on
issues of war and peace, foreign policy.
It's just a neo-conservative,
you know, pro-war foreign policy.
Um
but because I was not
an Obama supporter
and because it was the Obama
administration that went after me
on MSNBC, I was always always referred
to as John Kiriakou, who styles himself
a whistleblower.
Very offensive.
Who styles himself a whistleblower.
And then they were shocked
that I wouldn't come on their shows.
I was like, why would I? You insult me
every day
and then you want me to come on so you I
can be a punching bag for you. That's
not news.
So I refused.
And then
on the right
I was doing a podcast recently
um
at the home of the podcaster's parents.
Very wealthy people
very highly educated. And one of them
said it must be nice to get out of that
war zone for a day.
And I said, what do you mean?
Well, Washington, you know, the
president had to call out the National
Guards. It must be hell on earth down
there.
And I started laughing. And she said,
what?
And I said, Washington's one of the
safest big cities
in the Western world. There's no crime
problem in Washington. It's completely
made up.
It's just It's just for the for the
cameras.
And these National Guard troops, they're
only in the tourist areas where they get
the most visibility. They're not in the,
you know, drug dealing parts of the
city. It's just for for show.
And they looked at each other like,
"We've been duped."
Because every single night on Fox and
OAN and Newsmax, it's like this
hellscape that is Washington.
And it's just not.
It's just made up. You can't trust
anybody. People ask me all the time
where I get my news.
And the answer is
everywhere.
You can't rely on one or two or 10
outlets. You have to read them all. And
you have to become
well-versed enough
to know what to believe and why to
believe it.
So, I always go through my list and
people say, "Well, where where do you
get your news?" I say, "I start with
the New York Times, the Wall Street
Journal, the Washington Post, the LA
Times, the Pittsburgh Post-Gazette, the
Times of London, the Guardian.
And the the Greek press just because I'm
Greek and I enjoy the Greek press.
Then I go
to AP, UPI, Fox, CNN,
couple of others. And then I go to the
alternatives,
right? Um
reader-supported news, Consortium News,
Covert Action Magazine,
uh Dropsite News, The Intercept.
And then I just keep going. It takes me
2 hours every day just to skim
the 25 different websites that I need to
scan. And then if there's something
that's particularly interesting, like
a primary race, let's say,
then I have to go specifically to the
political press and to the to the
academic and and polling press.
And that's another hour. So, it takes
hours every single day just because you
can't believe anybody and you have to
come to your own conclusion.
>> Damn. Do you find that that gets
exhausting or is it something that you
love doing?
>> I've always loved it.
>> Yeah. Even when I was at the CIA, I
could not wait to get to the office in
the morning just to see what I had
missed overnight.
>> Yeah. So, you mentioned before that you
had people that were just basically
heckling you, just like as you're going
out, calling you names, labeling you
different things,
asking you to go on the show, and then
you're not obviously going on.
Did you find that it was quite
challenging being hated so much and
being like in a really like was was it
quite isolating being talk told all
these names and even your son getting
mad at you, like all all of this, like
did you find it was isolating?
>> No.
>> Why why not?
>> Because I had a core of
people who could not have possibly
supported me any more strongly.
A lot of them being former CIA
colleagues
telling me, "Keep doing it. You're doing
the right thing." I got I got an email
the day after I blew the whistle from a
retired Deputy Director of the CIA, of
the whole CIA.
And he said,
"You've chosen a difficult road.
I'm glad somebody did. I only wish I had
had the courage to do it myself."
And I saved it as a souvenir
to remind myself that I had done the
right thing.
You know, you and I were
you and I were talking before we started
filming
um about people's reactions to to this
kind of thing. And you just have to be
confident that that you're right.
And knowing that you're right, you just
let the chips fall.
And you get to see who's with you
and who's not with you. And sometimes
it's going to surprise you. But then you
come out on the other side stronger
knowing who who your friends really are.
>> Mhm.
>> Yeah, uh Matthew McConaughey
"I'd rather be hated for who I am than
to be than than to be applauded for
someone who I'm not.
>> [laughter]
>> Amen. He's 100% right.
>> Yeah, I think I think I look at this
right and if we talk about real
loneliness, real isolation, that's being
liked for someone that you're not
because you're getting praised for
someone that deep down isn't you. So you
don't even feel like people see you
because it's not even you who you're
showing. And I think, you know, as
you're sharing that today like
I had like a mini cancellation about a
year ago
where I got flamed for all these
different things and I remember I
doubled down and and like called them
all clowns. I was like, "No, like I
believe in what I said." And
I remember there was a a massive divide
that came from it where
people that was closest to me stopped
answering my calls, stopped liking
liking my posts. They stopped like they
didn't want to be associated with me
because they were fearful of
what people are going to think if they
were associated with me.
>> gotten that.
>> Yeah.
>> And and I would just remember
watching that and sitting that.
It was a shame, but at the same time
there's a level of peace because I I
felt this weight off my shoulders cuz I
was like, "I got nothing to hide that."
>> No, and you don't have to be something
different to different people. You can
just be yourself.
>> And then from that, what stemmed from it
was this freeing nature of being able to
just speak whatever was on my mind and
whatever felt true to me.
And that's what compounded everything
because at the end of the day, everyone
that likes me knows who I am because I'm
being real.
>> Yeah.
>> And then everyone that doesn't, well,
we were never going to be close anyway
because because because all I did was
just share my my thoughts and so it kind
of like made the connections in my life
stronger that were actually real and
then faded the ones that weren't. And
I don't know. I'm not sure if you relate
to that at all with with when you got to
come out.
>> Very much so. You know,
when I blew the whistle
I garnered a lot of support.
Even more like significantly more when I
got in legal trouble for it. But then
when I started writing from prison, I
started writing about
a lot of civil liberties issues and
corruption issues and stuff like that. I
wrote one
blog post that Ariana Huffington ran
about pedophiles.
And I said,
you know, now I'm I'm living among them.
And I see that they're
that they're beyond,
you know, saving.
And that society needs to be protected
from them. There's no cure for pedo-
pedophilia. You're not going to give
them therapy and then all of a sudden
they're not going to be interested in,
you know, having sex with children um
anymore. And so I said that I've come to
support something called um
community confinement.
So what they do is they they put mobile
homes
on the grounds of the prison.
And when you finish your your sentence,
you move into the mobile homes. So
you're technically not in in prison
anymore. You don't have to stand up for
the count times and, you know, stand in
line for inspection and all that stuff.
But you can't leave the grounds
because society needs to be protected
from you.
And the people that wrote to me and
said, "How dare you? They've paid their
debts to society and you're supposed to
be a civil libertarian. How dare you
want to confine these poor men?" And
it's like, "Sorry.
I'm right. You're wrong.
They can live in your house if you want
them out there.
But I don't want them around my
children."
>> Yeah.
I think there's certain lines that can't
be crossed and
pedophilia and
so anything to do with
with that is the is one of those ones.
>> Mhm.
>> Do you have any regrets?
>> No.
>> Why not?
>> I can't imagine
having regrets
polluting my thoughts 24 hours a day. I
made my bed. I am perfectly happy to lie
in it.
I accept what I did. I'm proud of what I
did. And I handled the consequences.
Thank God, knock on wood, things have
turned around for me.
Um but no.
I I won't allow myself to go through
life with regrets.
Nothing productive comes of that.
>> I like that.
What's your focus at the moment? Like in
life, what are you optimizing for?
>> I'm going to give you a different answer
than I would have have given you 6
months ago.
6 months ago it was about, you know,
continuing the fight for human rights
and civil rights and civil liberties.
Most important thing in my life. And
that's still very important. But
for for reasons that will never be clear
to me,
I somehow hit the
the YouTube algorithm sweet spot several
months ago.
And um
I'm getting more coverage than I've ever
gotten in my life. And I've been able to
actually make a living doing it. And so
I'm 61 years old. I'm finally going to
be in a position
to buy a decent house to live in and to
move on with my life and start to make
plans for retirement and live happily
ever after. So I'm going to continue to
write books and give speeches and advise
on films and and television series and
stuff like that.
I don't need to consider it to be work.
I like it so much. It just it's not work
to me.
I'm just going to keep doing it till I
can't anymore.
>> I appreciate you, dude. I feel like
I just want to commend you even to share
energy is the moment you walk in you
said probably joyful and and you got a
great great vibe about you and
yeah. Um I wish you all the best with
everything you're doing in the future.
Thanks for John Kiriakou. Thanks for
coming on the show, man.
>> Thank you.
>> Appreciate it.